<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Truth vindicated. Or, An answer to a letter sent from John Perrot out of Jamaica into England, &amp;c.</title>
            <author>R. F. (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1665</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95336</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3165</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R185760</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">47683511</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 47683511</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172969</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95336)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172969)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2660:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Truth vindicated. Or, An answer to a letter sent from John Perrot out of Jamaica into England, &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>R. F. (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666.</author>
                  <author>Watkins, Morgan, fl. 1653-1670.</author>
                  <author>Eccles, Solomon, 1618-1683.</author>
                  <author>Loe, Thomas.</author>
                  <author>Crisp, Stephen, 1628-1692.</author>
                  <author>Elson, John.</author>
                  <author>Coale, Josiah, 1632?-1668.</author>
                  <author>Newton, Samuel.</author>
                  <author>Roberts, Gerrard.</author>
                  <author>Green, Thomas, 1639?-1699.</author>
                  <author>Stodart, Amos.</author>
                  <author>Latey, Gilbert, 1626-1705.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Written in the Year, 1665.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"We have hereunto subscribed, whose Names are here under written. Richard Farneworth, Morgan Watkins, Solomon Eccles, Thomas Loe, Stephen Crispe, John Elson, J[o]siah Coale, Samuel Newt[o]n, Gerrard Roberts, Thomas Green, Am[o]r Stoddard, Gilbert Laty." -- p. 16.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, and with broken and missing type.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Friends' Library (London, England).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>J. P. --  (John Perrot), d. 1671? --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:172969:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Truth Vindicated. OR, AN ANSWER TO A LETTER <hi>SENT FROM JOHN PERROT O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>T OF</hi> JAMAICA INTO ENGLAND, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Written in the Year, 1665.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:172969:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:172969:2"/>
            <head>Truth Vindicated, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>WHereas a Letter of <hi>John Perrots</hi> from <hi>Jamaica</hi> to <hi>Mary Booth, John Coopland, Margaret Bradiſh</hi> and <hi>Francis Walker,</hi> bearing date the <hi>12th.</hi> of the <hi>4th.</hi> Moneth 1665. was produced by <hi>Robert Cobbet</hi> to <hi>Morgan Watkins</hi> in favour to <hi>John Perrot</hi> or intentionally for the clearing of the ſaid <hi>John</hi> from ſuch things as had been reported of him or charged againſt him to be inconſiſtant with Truth, and contrary to the leadings and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chings of the Principles and ſpirit of Truth, which we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and which he profeſſed though afterwards he apoſtatized or departed therefrom to hide himſelf under the Earth, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appear as in reſpect of the Lord and his Truth; ſo that the ſaid Letter by <hi>Robert Cobbet</hi> produced as aforeſaid doth not ſerve to the uſe, intent, and purpoſe for which it was produced, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to confirme and make good ſuch things as were reported of the ſaid <hi>John,</hi> or charged againſt him to be inconſiſtent with Truth, and contrary to the dealings of God and the experiences of his ſervants and meſſengers whom he hath ſent forth to declare and manifeſt truth unto many, who have in love received the ſame, and do manifeſt their faithfulneſs unto God by continuing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in under the Goſpel Diſpenſation.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The ſaid <hi>John Perrot</hi> (in that Letter) ſaid, Children I never told you otherwiſe at any time, and now tell you again weeping, that I never deemed my ſelf to be more then a man of Infirmity; if he was infirme in his judgment, councel, principles, doctrine, impoſitions, and practiſes, then he was unſound in the bottome or root of the matter, and contrary to the ſpirit and mind of Chriſt Jeſus, and therefore no fellow labourer with God in the work of the Miniſtry; for they who are acquainted with God, and have received the ſpirit and power of God as the true Goſpel Miniſters do, and aforetime did, to enable them to be as
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:172969:3"/>
workers together with him in their Miniſtration received of God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 1. who hath made them able Miniſters of the New Teſtament, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 5, 6. enabling them for his own ſervice that they are as workers together with him, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 1. In all things approving themſelves as the Miniſters of God, their ſufficiency is of him; but they who ſpeak of themſelves and act from their own wiſdom and reaſon, and the mans part only, and not from the ſpirit and power of God, are no more indeed then men of Infirmity as in reſpect of their Miniſtration; And if <hi>John</hi> was any thing more then a man of Infirmity, and if he was not unſound and infirme upon the aforeſaid conſideration, why ſhould he have made mention of it upon the account that he hath done, ſeeing he hath ſo much cryed down man, and would have man to be nothing, but the Lord to be all, who is not unſound or infirme in any thing, if <hi>John</hi> was no more but a man of Infirmity then he ſpoke of himſelf, and his ſpeaking, ſtanding, and acting was of himſelf, and ſo his Natural parts and abilities were his ſufficiency, therefore it was of ſelf and not of the Lord; and ſelf ſufficiency we deny as inconſiſtent with Truth, in reſpect of the Miniſtry, and acknowledge to the Lord and his power to be our ſufficiency, not that we are ſufficient of our ſelves to think any thing as of our ſelves, but our ſufficiency is of God, who alſo hath made us able Miniſters of the New Teſtament.</p>
            <p>And whereas he (in that Letter) ſaid unto them (by way of accuſation of others) whilſt many have come forth in fury as an Hoſt of armed Men with Inſtruments of War in attempts and purſuits to ſlay me, yet are they no more in mine eye then as Children labouring to beat the air. Whereby it appears that <hi>John</hi> in his own account hath not been hurt, nor at all harmed by them that he hath ſo falſly accuſed, who deny that they have gone forth in any fury as an hoſt of armed Men in purſuites with Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of War to ſlay him, neither could he prove it, who turned falſe accuſer of the brethren, and that is the work of old Antichriſt and for joyning with him therein, he might expect a reward from the hand of the Lord according to his doings. And whereas he ſaid many are ſtriving in an evil day. That may ſtand for himſelf and thoſe that ſtrives on his behalf by an evil ſpirit to ſow the feed of diſſention, and lead people into a ſeparation from that which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:172969:3"/>
God leadeth into: And that indeed is an evil work which he and others were ſtriving to accompliſh, but the Lord is blaſting and will ſpoil their Antichriſtian deſign.</p>
            <p>And whereas in that Letter he ſaid unto them it ſhall go well with you and me if we all keep in the root of their matter, and in it be hid under the Earth till the winter is paſt and gone, is not that to make no appearance for God, neither in meeting or prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, or any thing elſe that may expoſe them to ſufferings for Righteouſneſs ſake, if ſo, is not that an Antichriſtian trick of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, and altogether inconſiſtent with Truth. And did not <hi>John</hi> lead you to forſake the practiſe and teſtimony of Truth, and center under the Earth in the root of deceit, from whence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds unſoundneſs and infirmity in Councel, Doctrine, Judgment and Practiſe, which is nought in the foundation thereof, and root of the matter, and what was amiſs and nought in the foundation could never be made good by <hi>John</hi>'s confirmation. And if by the root of the matter be meant the principle of Truth, and the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly gift or Talent, which God hath committed to any for his own uſe and ſervice to beget and gather to the brightneſs of his riſings, that is neither to be hid in the Earth, nor laid up in a Napkin untill troubles, trials, afflictions, and perſecutions for Righteouſneſs ſake (which may be accounted the Winter) be paſt and gone: Therefore <hi>John</hi>'s judgment and councel in the caſe was unſound and infirme, and of the mans part in him, which as he himſelf accounted was never otherwiſe; therefore inconſiſtent with Truth, and not according to the direction, judgment and councel of the ſpirit and power of God (in man) which is ſound and firme, or elſe it would ſignifie nothing for a ſouls inſtruction, confirmation, ſatisfaction and conſolation. And that ſpirit which leads people who have received any heavenly gift or talent from God wherein they have appeared in principle and practiſe on the behalf of the Lord, to hide the ſame under the Earth again, ſo as to diſappear in reſpect of the work of the Lord by hiding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves under the Earth, and ſo lie hid in obſcurity for their ſelf ſafely untill troubles, trials, afflictions, and perſecutions ceaſe and be gone, is not the ſpirit that we have received of God, but a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary ſpirit, as <hi>John Perrots</hi> was, which we have already denyed, and by the truth it's condemned, for they who hide themſelves
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:172969:4"/>
under the Earth as <hi>John</hi> adviſed to do, are covered with Earth and deceit, and not with the ſpirit and power of truth, and the woe againſt them is already pronounced, for woe unto them that cover with a covering, but not of my ſpirit, ſaith the Lord: And it's very evident and plain unto us that <hi>John Perrot</hi> was as that branch (he ſpoke of) which hath ſtriven to bud out of its natural ſeaſon, and that is the cauſe his bloſſomes did fall, and its boughs wither according to his own reaſon.</p>
            <p>And whereas <hi>John Perrot</hi> in that Letter ſaid, I was once a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Truth and Righteouſneſs amongſt you and many others, and was faithful in what I did, though ſomethings of the Myſtery of the Goſpel could not be borne of my Elders.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> What is that to the purpoſe if he was once a Miniſter of Righteouſneſs or numbred amongſt them that are ſo, ſeeing that by tranſgreſſion he fell from it, and turned down under the Earth to hide himſelf there, and turned enemy to them who are Miniſters of Righteouſneſs, and in preaching the Word are inſtant both in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon according to the charge given before the Lord; he is no more to be accounted of: <hi>Judas</hi> was once num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred amongſt the Apoſtles of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and had received part of the Miniſtry and Apoſtleſhip, <note place="margin">Act. 1. 16, 17, 20.</note> but he afterwards by tranſgreſſion fell from it, and his end was miſerable, and he no more accounted of but <note place="margin">Act 1. 23, 24. 25. 26</note> as a Traytor and an Apoſtate; however that part of the Miniſtry and Apoſtleſhip which he fell from, was deſirable and prayed for, ſo that truth is truth, though ſome may betray their truſt and depart or fall from it, and it will outlive all deceit and Apoſtates; and as for thoſe things of the Myſtery of the Goſpel he ſpoke of, which he ſaid could not be borne by his Elders, what were they but ſuch things as tended to faction, as teaching people to be irreverent in keeping on their Hats at Prayer: And foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as he acknowledged Elders he ſhould have kept in a place of ſubjection, and not have preſumed to impoſe things upon them, for the Lord hath required that the Younger do ſubmit to the Elder; and what is it that maketh true Elderſhip but the eternal Spirit and power of Truth, that doth open the myſtery unto them to whom its given to know the Myſteries of the Kingdom: And how durſt <hi>John</hi> riſe up in falſe accuſations and judgment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:172969:4"/>
them as he hath done, did not that beſpeak great pride in his heart, and that he aſpired to be great in a ſelf exaltation, and now the Lord hath abaſed him for ſo doing.</p>
            <p>And whereas he ſaid, I am not provoked unto haſt ſeeing all times will have their Revolution, and I wait untill a change cometh, and a renewed commiſſion is given from above, that if I ſound the Trump of the Lord it ſhall not be at uncertainty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It ſeems that what he ſaid then and before was but at un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty, and he was no Miniſter of Truth and Righteouſneſs then in his own account, nor in the account of <hi>Robert Cobbet,</hi> who confeſſed that he had jealouſies of <hi>John Perrot</hi> before us, and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter jealouſies then we had, and ſaid he was then no Miniſter, for his commiſſion was ended, what change was it that <hi>John</hi> waited for to ſee come, was it to ſee perſecutions and afflictions over and be gone; and what commiſſion was it he waited for ſeeing that he hath formerly ſaid that pleading the cauſe that is truly righteous, and bearing his teſtimony of the power of love was finiſhed, and if that was finiſhed as he ſaid it was, would he have had a commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to plead the cauſe that is unrighteous, and to bear teſtimony againſt the power of love; if ſo, he might expect that from old Antichriſt, for the Lord would never grant him any ſuch, and becauſe he hath rejected the Lord in rejecting his Councel, he was rejected of God ſo as to be any Miniſter of his.</p>
            <p>And whereas (in the Letter aforeſaid) he ſaid to <hi>Mary Booth,</hi> In reading thy particular lines I find that thy love would have me become yet again very honourable in <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Seeing he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged <hi>Mary Booths</hi> love in wiſhing his Reſtoration from that which renders him diſhonourable in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ought not he to have accepted her love ſo as to have ſought to return to that which in her apprehenſion he was fallen from, for it appeared that both in her and his own accompt he was degenerated and fallen from what he once either really was, or at leaſt was by them apprehended ſo to be, for <hi>Robert Cobbet</hi> ſuſpected <hi>John,</hi> and had jealouſies of him, before he ſo fell; And when that he was fallen the love of <hi>Mary Booth</hi> in wiſhing that he might become once again very honourable in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> beſpoke in her mind unto others that he was fallen from that which in her account once made him honourable in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and that he was then diſhonourable therein, or amongſt them; and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:172969:5"/>
her love deſiring that he might become once again very honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> beſpoke that he ſtood in need of a Reſtoration unto that which he had loſt by degeneration, which thing he told her he ſought not, having once ſeen the great evil and ſnare that hath attended ſuch a condition, both as touching what it might prove to others and to himſelf; and for that cauſe (he ſaid) it was beſt to him to be the moſt contemptible, and it was with him at that preſent to walk and live both in reſpect of judgment and fellowſhip void of the appearance of having it with any Creature.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Whereby it appeared that an honorable eſtate and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in <hi>Iſrael</hi> was not in his account to be ſought or deſired after, becauſe it might be attended with danger, thereby beſpeaking diſtruſt in his mind, as if God could not preſerve out of the ſnare. 2. That it was better for him to be in that which made him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible, then in that which makes honorable in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> was contemptible enough, when by tranſgreſſion he was fallen from what he received, as in reſpect of the Miniſtry, the which if he had abode in, might have made him honorable, doth it therefore follow that becauſe <hi>Judas</hi> might have been honorable if he had abode in the Miniſtry received, but being attended with temptations departed from the Lord, and by tranſgreſſion fell from his Miniſtry, (and into compliance with the ſpirit of the World, and ſo became contemptible and a ſtink to this day, as ſuch are and will be who depart from the truth, and walk in <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> way of Apoſtacy) that therefore the way of the Lord, and the work of the Miniſtry, is not to be deſired and if any fall from it that its beſt for them to be contemptible in not ſeeking or endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a Reſtoration, if the love of the Lord thorough any deſire it, or if the Lord call thereunto. And thirdly, that in reſpect of judgment, and fellowſhip he ſaid he did walk, and live void of the appearance of having it with any Creature, and did ſtand ſtill for a ſeaſon as one dumb and mute, looking round about him to ſee which way the world mans mind would roul, which is not ſound Doctrine, for God is Light, and they that walk in the Light as he is in the Light they have fellowſhip one with another, who would therefore have depended upon <hi>John Perrot,</hi> except ſuch as declined in their hearts from the Lord, and incline to the world, and are
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:172969:5"/>
ſeeking an occaſion to forſake the truth and break off from the way of the Lord, whoſe minds are preparing for Ranteriſme, and to walk in the way of ſeparation from God and his People, by following a ſpirit of deluſion, to turn unto any thing that ſuites with a fleſhly communion according to the worldly imaginations, under pretence of liberty in a myſtery which is not bounded by the ſpirit of truth and holineſs, and let them take heed leaſt the ſpirit of deluſion which entred <hi>John</hi> do enter them, ſo as to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them to center in Rantiſme: for he ſaid, Children be not offended if I ask ſomething that the light in you may in due time anſwer you, did God by his light in us draw us from any thing of appearance, or the formal cuſtomes outward which are not of worſhip in themſelves, but through the croſs which ſtood againſt our carnal affections in them things, and now if we are naturalized to a cuſtome which the natural affection taketh part of, is not the croſs to be to that, and would it not be now a croſs to us to do thoſe things which were never ſin ſimply in themſelves, which once through the croſs we were led from, conſider all manner of geſtures, ſalutations, and external, formal appearances for the great myſtery of the Goſpel, and Righteouſneſs, thereof is held in the croſs, which touching many things no man can meaſure in another.</p>
            <p>What's that to the purpoſe if no man can meaſure ſuch things the ſpirit of God in man, and the true meaſuring time can meaſure theſe things in all that appertain to the Goſpel, and the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs thereof. Therefore it was deceit in <hi>John</hi> that ſo ſpoke, and made the aforeſaid inquiry whereby they might if they were not blinded in their underſtandings ſee how the old ranting ſpirit was making way for its deſign, and how the Serpent is <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ing and twining to wind in his ſubtlety, and thereby to turn their minds from the ſimplicity of the Truth for the fitting of them to conforme to any thing but truth, in the life and power thereof, as if God did by the light of his Son diſcover an evil, and lead from the ſame, and afterwards lead back from the good into the evil again: It ſeems that the continuation in any practice, doctrine, or thing that God by the light of Chriſt Jeſus doth lead men into, and work them into love with the ſame, was accounted by <hi>Iohn</hi> a forme, and to be naturalized into the thing, for which God may
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:172969:6"/>
croſs Men, and lead them therefrom again, becauſe they are in love with the ſame which was but <hi>John</hi>'s fancy and vain imagination, and contrary to ſound Doctrine, for ſaid the Apoſtle and Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt unto <hi>Timothy,</hi> That good thing which was committed unto thee keep by the Holy Ghoſt which dwelleth in us: This thou knoweſt that all they which are in <hi>Aſia</hi> be turned away from me, of whom are <hi>Phygellus</hi> and <hi>Hermogenes,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 14, 15. for ſome are already turned aſide after Sathan, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 15. as <hi>John Perrot</hi> did, and they that received his ſpirit have done, who may take notice of their examples to be ſuch as aforeſaid, who turned away from the Apoſtles of Chriſt, and turned aſide from the Truth after Satan: But the Apoſtle exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Timothy</hi> to take heed to himſelf at ſuch a time, and unto his Doctrine to continue therein, for in ſo doing he ſhould both ſave himſelf and them that heard him, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 16. And they who have received a Miniſtry from God are to continue in the ſame, and in preaching the Word to be inſtant both in ſeaſon and out of ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to reprove, rebuke, exhort, with all long ſuffering and Doctrine, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 2. and not do as <hi>John Perrot</hi> did, if the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuation in the Doctrines, Principles and Practices which the light of God leads into, became a cuſtome in <hi>John</hi>'s eſteem, and if be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the outward man be naturalized into love with the Truth, or made conformable to the inner Man, and be affected with the ſame, muſt be croſt and broken off to go aſide into Men's traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and the worlds vanities again, <hi>John</hi> therein was greatly miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, for as God by his Light and Spirit of Grace within us hath led us from the Will-Worſhips, by the ſame light he will never lead us into them again: 2. As God by the Light of Chriſt in us hath led us in the Croſs to our wills to keep on our Hats and not put them off in reſpect of honouring Mens perſons, he will not by the ſame light and ſpirit lead us to put them off again upon the ſame conſideration: 3. As God hath led us by the light of Chriſt in us to aſſemble and meet together to wait upon him in the way of his worſhip in the croſs to our wills, he will never by the ſame light and ſpirit of grace lead us from the continuation of that godly practice, though we be affected with the ſame, becauſe of his preſence with us who doth enjoyne his People to continue therein; for it is the duty of the People of God to continue in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:172969:6"/>
the ſame, becauſe the Lord hath led into it, and doth own them therein, and it is a danger to be negligent in that reſpect through the workings of Satan, for God will not lead us from the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation in that godly practice, though the Natural Man may par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the knowledge and virtue of God with the Spiritual man, for the Earth as well as Heaven ſhall be filled with the knowledge of God as it is written: 4. The ſame light and ſpirit of Grace in us that hath led us into acquaintance with God, and hath led us to put off our Hats in time of Prayer, and owned us therein all along from the firſt to this day in ſuch a practice in our ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the Lord in the Aſſemblies of his people from whoſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and heavenly power we have received many refreſhings and Teſtimonies for our confirmation, ſatisfaction and conſolation will never lead us to keep on our Hats in the time of Prayer in the Aſſemblies of the Saints in oppoſition to Gods preſent and former leadings, did not <hi>John</hi> go about by his Imaginations to change the Truth of God into a lie if he could, and to ſet the Lord in oppoſition to the leadings of his own ſpirit and power, which he could not do, and to make God as changable as he was contrary to the Lords own ſayings, who hath ſaid, I am God, I change not, therefore ye ſons of Jacob are not conſumed: Might not <hi>Iohn</hi> have as well ſaid, that God would not have People to be fixed and centred in an unchangable thing ſo as to continue therein, and in the practiſes that he leadeth into, and confirmeth them in under a ſpiritual diſpenſation: And likewiſe might he not as well have ſaid that the ſame light and ſpirit of Chriſt Jeſus that hath led Men out of the vanities and wickedneſs of the World into love with God and his Truth, may lead them from Him and his Truth again, becauſe they are naturalized or made conformable to it, ſo as to abide and continue therein, and are in love with him: Oh dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Doctrine! for they that are juſt and faithful to God muſt continue in that and thoſe things which the eternal Spirit and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of God hath led them into, and enjoyned them by his own Spirit therein to abide, that they may not be as wandring Stars, but fixed in the Firmament of Truth, and keep their ſtanding and place in the power of God, ſo will their Conſciences be kept void of offence in the ſight of God as they ſtand approved in his ſight by continuing in that and thoſe practices and things which the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:172969:7"/>
Lord leadeth his People into, and enjoynes them to continue and abide therein, under his own ſpiritual and heavenly diſpenſation.</p>
            <p>And whereas <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaid, that the <hi>Myſtery</hi> of the Goſpel and the Righteouſneſs thereof is held in the Croſs, and ſaid keep to your own, and ſee that for Conſcience ſake ye have no more reſpect (through any cuſtome, form of greeting or ſalutation) to pleaſe one ſort of People paſſing only under one denomination, then caution in your hearts by ſuch cuſtome to diſpleaſe others of other denominations, and if that offend man you are to bear the Croſs, which the <hi>Iewes</hi> would naile you unto.</p>
            <p>If by the <hi>Iewes</hi> he did mean and intend good ancient old friends who continue and abide in the Truth, as his Writing imports; and if by nailing them to the Croſs (who are given to change their Principles and Practices as he did) be to fix and faſten them to the power of Truth, or Myſtery of the Goſpel, and the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs thereof, (which is held in the Croſs that they may continue and abide in the ſame, be the nailing of them thereto that he ſpoke of, that they may not run into deluſions and turn from the Truth to conforme unto and comply with all ſorts of People under eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry denomination in that which the Spirit and power of Truth doth not allow of and own, wherein are they to be blamed? for ſo fixing and faſting them to the Truth for their eſtabliſhment, confirmation and continuation therein? But if by the <hi>Iewes</hi> he did mean the enemies of Chriſt, and accounted good friends to be ſuch; and if by the nailing of them to the Croſs be to expoſe them to ſufferings for Righteouſneſs, as the <hi>Iewes</hi> did Chriſt by nailing him to the Croſs; he was greatly miſtaken, and did falſly accuſe the brethren, and ran himſelf into confuſion and ſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, and ſo was enſnared by the words of his mouth; and if all ſorts of People under every denomination, who have an outward profeſſion of Godlineſs muſt be conformed unto and complyed with in ſuch manner of geſtures, ſalutations, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal, formal appearances for the pleaſing of them in that and thoſe things which the light and ſpirit of God doth not allow of nor own where is the Croſs taken up and ſtood in, to thoſe things, for as the light of Chriſt doth diſcover the evil and croſs the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal affections when they would run out into ſuch actions as the truth doth condemn, ſo they who forſake that w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> the Lord leadeth
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:172969:7"/>
into, they run in their own will, and carnal affections into that which the World's fellow ſhip ſtands in, whereby they go through their fleſhly wiſdom and natural affection to croſs the Light and Spirit of the Lord, and ſo they forſake the true Croſs, which is of power to crucifie them to the World, and the World unto them; and that's the cauſe why the enmity remains, and a life is pleaded for and ſought after, which the ſpirit and power of Truth doth condemn. And whereas <hi>Iohn Perrot</hi> in that Letter hath ſaid my heart meditates the thing that is juſt and equal among all, but can hardly yet come to this very rule, becauſe of preſent evil in me, which I cannot eſcape, which is of having a greater reſpect in the general of the ſatisfaction of <hi>Quakers</hi> in me rather then others, but this muſt be overcome, and I wait for it, though none have perſecuted me as <hi>Quakers</hi> have done.</p>
            <p>It ſeems <hi>Iohn</hi> had not then wholly and altogether gotten into a perfect ſtate of Rantiſme becauſe he had not altogether ſlain the witneſs and got over the ſame, ſo as to conforme unto and run into any thing that truth doth not own, &amp; account it no ſin, for it ſeems the witneſs in him that did bear witneſs unto the People of God, reproachfully called <hi>Quakers,</hi> was not wholly overcome in him at that time, becauſe he could not but have a greater reſpect in him to them then unto others, but he accounted it an evil in him to have a reſpect to the <hi>Quakers</hi> more then to others, &amp; he expected to overcome that, and waited for it; who was turned to be a falſe accuſer of them, for he ſaid he never was ſo perſecuted by any as by them; whereby it appears that he never was perſecuted to do him any harme, neither hath he been in any wiſe wronged or hurt by them; for he hath falſly accuſed the brethren in that thing, and hath before cleared them from the force of the ſaid falſe accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, confeſſing in effect that they never did him any harme: But however the Innocent People of God reproachfully called <hi>Quakers</hi> are clcar from his Aſperſions, and do deny all perſecutions, and he alſo hath cleared them whom he hath ſo unjuſtly accuſed by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging that they have done him no harme as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>And as for that unity he ſpoke of or having unity with candid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of heart of <hi>Iohn Swinton</hi> in a paper of his lately given forth to <hi>Iſrael;</hi> he hath ſo much the more diſcovered and manifeſted his ſpirit in oppoſition to friends; and <hi>Iohn Swinton</hi> may take
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:172969:8"/>
notice what ſpirits they are whom he hath ſo gratified by his paper as aforeſaid: But it's certainly true that offences muſt come, and the Woe is pronounced from God againſt them by whom they do come. And it's certainly true that the enemy did heretofore enter <hi>Iohn Perrot,</hi> and made uſe of him as an Inſtrument, to offend many of the little ones that believes in the Lord Jeſus, and to cauſe the way of Truth to be evil ſpoken of, and he might expect to bear the diſpleaſure of the Lord for ſo doing; and as for <hi>Iohn Swinton</hi> in what he hath written againſt Friends the Lord doth not own it, for it did not proceed from his own power and ſpirit; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the witneſs of God in his People do deny it, and it cannot be received into the ſpirit and power of Truth, becauſe it proceeded not from it, ſo that he hath not the anſwer of God in the hearts of his People for its acceptation, but is teſtified againſt, becauſe it is for condemnation; therefore <hi>Iohn Swinton</hi> had better never have writen the ſame, but it may be a warning to him for the time to come to take heed how he preſumes to do any ſuch thing.</p>
            <p>And as for the ground and cauſe of <hi>Iohn Perrot</hi> forſaking his Miniſtry, he ſaid, he had cauſe as well natural in Manhood and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der affection to his Wife and Children, as ſpiritual in obedience to that life which drew him for example ſake to labour in his proper ſtation. It ſeems his ground was firſt earthly, and proceeded from a Natural cauſe, that was the firſt motive to lay down his Miniſtry, <hi>viz.</hi> in reſpect of his Wife and Children, not conſidering that they who have received a Miniſtry from God are to continue faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the Lord in their Miniſtration, and in preaching the Word, to be inſtant in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, notwithſtanding Wife and Children; for Chriſt hath ſaid he that loves any thing more then me is not worthy of me; and that which a man moſt loves that he is moſt conſtant unto, and can do the moſt for, and do it moſt freely. And as for the ſecond cauſe, it was but a pretence and meer deceit, as if God ſhould give a Miniſtry to one, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards lead him from it again to be covered over with earth as an example to others, which is contrary to the truth, and to the command of the ſpirit of Chriſt in the true Goſpel Miniſters, who ſaid walk as ye have us for Examples. And they did not do as <hi>Iohn Perrot</hi> did, for if he ſhould have been followed as an example, then all the Miniſters of the Goſpel of Chriſt might forſake their
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:172969:8"/>
Miniſtry according to <hi>John</hi>'s account, and turn into the Earthly Imployments, and lie hid under the Earth, and no more appear for the Lord and his Truth; ſo that it appears his Miniſtry ſtood in his own will to diſpenſe with, and now he is laid aſide as one uſeleſs. And whereas he ſaid, he could not bear; that the Goſpel ſhould be chargable on his part, but was willing to lay forth his all for the glory of Gods ſake that was concerned therein. That's but deceit that ſpoke in him, for who hath been chargable like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him upon that conſideration, and then he had forſaken that which he made ſo chargable to his ſhame and confuſion, and is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into the Earth again, which is his proper ſtation or place ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his own ſaying. And as for <hi>Iohn Harwood, Iohn White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe,</hi> and <hi>Dorothy White,</hi> they are denyed, diſowned, and judged by <hi>Robert Cobbet</hi> as he hath acknowledged to ſome of us; and we do deny them to be of us, and hereby declare that we do not own them but do teſtifie againſt them, and all ſuch factious ſpirits.</p>
            <p>And whereas <hi>Iohn Perrot</hi> in that Letter from <hi>Iamaica</hi> ſaid, he was toſſed on every hand yet not moved by any. If he was not moved by any, hath he not hereby contradicted them who ſay that Friends drove him from the Truth, to drive a man from the Truth is to move him, but Friends did not drive him from the Truth; and <hi>Iohn</hi> in effect hath cleared them from ſuch an aſperſion; ſaying, though he was toſſed on every hand, yet not moved by any; if not moved by any then not removed or driven from the Truth by Friends; therefore <hi>Iohn</hi> in effect hath cleared them from the force of ſuch an accuſation or charge as aforeſaid. And whereas <hi>Iohn Perrot</hi> ſaid in that Letter, I am given to be this day the reproach of many. Who hath given him to be ſo? did he not give himſelf unto the deluſions of Satan to be an occaſion of the reproach of many? and who are they that he was a reproach unto? a reproach he was, and one that was given, to change both Miniſtry, Doctrine and practiſe, which God hath led his People into, and enjoyned them to continue in, and not do as <hi>Iohn</hi> did, (and thoſe that followed him for their example) have done; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he hath been a reproach to the truth, &amp; to them that keep their firſt love, who abide in the Covenant of Grace, and he might be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of his doings, and ſo may all they who joyned with him in that and thoſe things that tends to deviſion and ſeparation from God and his Truth, and to bring a reproach upon them who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:172969:9"/>
and abide in the Principles, Doctrines, practice and power of God received. And ſeeing that <hi>John Perrot</hi> by hearkning to Satan and in yielding unto him as the principal cauſe of his remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val from truth, who being thereby ſo removed was the inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal cauſe or only man who made ſuch diſſention amongſt Friends that were in ſo great love and unity before, and hath led many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Markes of ſeparation, which God doth not lead his People in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: And ſeeing that <hi>John</hi> did become a reproach unto many as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, this may teach all ſuch as are preſerved out of his ſpirit, and the deceivable workings and ways of Satan to mind their ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtneſs to and continuation with God, his Truth and People in that and thoſe things which makes for unity peace and reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and they may for ever priſe the love, mercy and power of God, which preſerved them that they did not meddle with up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding and following the fantafies and imaginations of him the ſaid <hi>J<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hn,</hi> or any of them that are given to change, and do as he hath done, and it may be a ſhame to them who either follow or plead for ſuch an example, ſo as to mind the light of Chriſt Jeſus to move them to conſider how they went out from unity with us and in obedience to the manifeſtation, direction, and calling of the Principle and Spirit of truth, to return from whence they are fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, and from thoſe markes of ſeparation, and from ſuch things as <hi>John</hi>'s impoſitions, example and practice in his toſſed eſtate and condition ſince he began to quarrel and wrangle with Friends they have been led into, which we and the truth cannot own.</p>
            <p>And to teſtifie our love to the Lord, his Truth, and People, who continue and abide in unity and peace with God, and one with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other in the refreſſing life, love, virtue and power thereof, and in that godly order and practiſe which the Lord hath led us into, and by his own ſpirit enjoyned us therein to continue and abide; and in teſtimony againſt all ſuch ſpirits, actions and things aforementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned meant &amp; intended as do devide and ſeparate from the truth, and turn to the reproach of our profeſſion, and to the diſhonour of God whom we profeſſe, and to the turning of the weak out of the way of the Lord and to the reproach of his People. We have hereunto ſubſcribed, whoſe Names are here under written.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Richard Farneworth, Morgan Watkins, Solomon Eccles, Thomas Loe, Stephen Criſpe, John Elſon, J<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſi<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h Coale, Samuel Newton, Gerrard Roberts, Thomas Green, Am<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r Stodard, Gilbert Laty.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
